Guide to the Allen Building Takeover Oral History collection UA.31.04.0016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allen Building Takeover Oral History collection
1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Yannella, Don
UA.31.04.0016
1.5 Linear Feet
On February 13, 1969, Duke University students in the Afro-American Society occupied the the main administration building to bring attention to the needs of black students. These needs included an African American studies department, a black student union, and increased enrollment and financial support for black students. This and subsequent events became known as the Allen Building Takeover. The Allen Building Takeover Oral History Collection includes oral histories conducted by Duke student Don Yannella in 1985 leading to his thesis Race Relations at Duke University and the Allen Building Takeover. The collection includes the original interview tapes, transcripts of the some of the interviews, and use copies of several of the original recordings.
Biographical / Historical
On the morning of February 13, 1969, between 50 and 75 black students entered the Allen Building and proceeded to barricade and occupy it. They renamed the building the Malcolm X Liberation School. The students issued a list of demands to the administration, [which included an accredited African-American Studies Department, a black dorm, a black student union, an increase in enrollment and financial support for black students, protection from police harassment, and better working conditions for non-academic staff of the University]. Provost Marcus Hobbs read a statement to the students at about 3:30 PM, urging them to leave the building within one hour to begin a peaceful discussion of the issues. Sometime after 5 o'clock, after a warning from Provost Hobbs that they would face legal ramifications for staying, the students decided to exit. Although the exit was peaceful, a large crowd of mostly white students had gathered outside the building during the day, and this crowd and the police became entangled. The police fired tear gas on the students.
Immediately following the police action, students met to discuss how to proceed. Many students and faculty were upset by the administration's support of the police action; other students and faculty felt that the takeover of the Allen Building was lawless and disruptive. Those who supported the Takeover called for a three day strike on campus and offered alternative classes. Students opposed to the Takeover urged fellow students to attend classes as normal. The administration attempted to calm the campus and address some of the demands posed by the Takeover participants. President Knight addressed Duke on the campus radio station, WDBS.
Afro-American Society and administration members met several times to begin forming an African-American Studies program. The two parties could not reach an agreement on what type of committee should oversee the program. On March 10, a group of students marched to downtown Durham along with students from other colleges to protest the situation. The next day, March 11, 1969, students again went to downtown Durham and marched with other students and Durham residents. The march turned violent, with store windows smashed and other damage to property. The mayor put a curfew on the city for several days.
Dozens of Duke's black students threatened to leave campus following the lack of agreement on the African-American Studies program. They instead planned to attend the Malcolm X Liberation University, a newly-developed school led by community activist Howard Fuller. However, the students soon reversed their decision and decided to remain at Duke University. On March 19, a University Hearing Committee found the students who had occupied the building guilty of violating university regulations. All defendants were sentenced to one year of probation.
In 1985, Duke student Don Yannella conducted oral history interviews with a number of individuals at Duke who were involved with or present during the events of the Allen Building Takeover. He used the information gathered in these interviews to write a senior honors thesis entitled Race Relations at Duke University and the Allen Building takeover.
[Taken from text written by Valerie Gillispie as part of the web exhibit, Campus Protest: Duke University, 1967-1969.]
Conditions Governing Access
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Portions of this collection are restricted due to the absence of a release form from the persons interviewed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection was received as a gift in 1985.
Related Materials
Race relations at Duke University and the Allen Building takeover, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Allen Building Takeover Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Scope and Contents
The Allen Building Takeover Oral History Collection includes materials collected by Duke student Don Yannella while writing his senior thesis in 1985. The oral histories offer first-hand accounts of and reactions to the Takeover from Duke students, staff, administrators, and members of the Durham community.
The interviews were recorded on cassette tapes, and these original tapes are in Box 1. Access copies and transcripts for many of the interviews are included; listening copies are in Box 2 and transcripts are in Box 3.
African American student movements; African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Political activity; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; African Americans -- North Carolina -- History -- 1964-; Civil rights demonstrations -- North Carolina -- Durham; College students, Black -- North Carolina; Oral histories (document genre); Race relations.; Sound recordings; Student participation in administration; Students -- Political activity; Yannella, Don; Armstrong, Brenda E. (Brenda Estelle); Cahow, Clark R.; Cell, John Whitson, 1935-2001; Cook, Samuel DuBois, 1927-; DeMik, Harry; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Afro-American Society; Duke University -- Buildings -- History; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Duke University -- Students -- Social conditions; Griffith, William; Hammond, Sam; Kerckhoff, Alan C.; Newsome, Clarence G. (Clarence Geno), 1950-; Pye, A. Kenneth; Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent; Turner, William Clair; Watson, Richard L., 1914-2000; Williams, Fred J.; Williams, Janice
- Armstrong, Brenda, January 31, 1985; 1
  - Brenda Armstrong Interview: Cassette 4, Side A, January 31, 1985 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Interview restricted due to lack of signed release form from the interviewee.
  - Brenda Armstrong Interview: Transcript, January 31, 1985 (Box 4)
- Budd, Louis, circa 1985; 2
  - Budd Louis Interview: Transcript, circa 1985 (Box 3)
- Cahow, Clark, January 23, 1985; 3
  - Clark Cahow Interview: Cassette 3, Side A, January 23, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Clark Cahow Interview: cassette use copy, Side A, January 23, 1985, copied 11/03 (Box 2)
  - Clark Cahow Interview: Transcript, January 23, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Clark Cahow Interview: CD use copy, January 23, 1985 (Box 2)
- Campbell, Tom, February 8, 1985; 4
  - Tom Campbell Interview: Cassette 5, Side A, February 8, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Tom Campbell Interview: Transcript, February 8, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Tom Campbell Interview: CD use copy, February 8, 1985 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    CD not working.
- Cell, John, March 7, 1985; 5
  - John Cell Interview: Cassette 12, Side A, March 7, 1985 (Box 1)
  - John Cell Interview: CD use copy, March 7, 1985 (Box 2)
- Cook, Samuel, March 1, 1985; 6
  - Samuel Cook Interview pt. 1: Cassette 8, Side A, March 1, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Samuel Cook Interview pt. 2: Cassette 8, Side B, March 1, 1985 (Box 1)
- DeMik, Harry, February 12, 1985; 7
  - Harry DeMik Interview: Cassette 5, Side B, February 12, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Harry DeMik Interview: Transcript, February 12, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Harry DeMik Interview: CD use copy, February 12, 1985 (Box 2)
- Griffith, William, March 5, 1985; 8
  - William Griffith Interview: Cassette 11, Side A, March 5, 1985 (Box 1)
- Hammond, Samuel, February 13, 1985; 9
  - Samuel Hammond Interview: Cassette 6, Side B, February 13, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Samuel Hammond Interview: CD, February 13, 1985 (Box 2)
- Kerckhoff, Alan, March 4, 1985; 10
  - Alan Kerckhoff Interview: Cassette 10, Side B, March 4, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Alan Kerckhoff Interview: cassette use copy, Side B, March 4, 1985, copied 11/03 (Box 2)
  - Alan Kerckhoff Interview: CD use copy, March 4, 1985 (Box 2)
- Newsome, Clarence, January 31, 1985; 11
  - Clarence Newsome Interview: Cassette 4, Side B, January 31, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Clarence Newsome Interview: Transcript, January 31, 1985 (Box 4)
- Pye, Kenneth, March 2, 1985; 12
  - Kenneth Pye Interview pt. 1: Cassette 9, Side A, March 2, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Kenneth Pye Interview pt. 1: CD use copy, March 2, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Kenneth Pye Interview pt. 2: Cassette 9, Side B, March 2, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Kenneth Pye Interview pt. 2: CD use copy, March 2, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Kenneth Pye Interview: Transcript, March 2, 1985 (Box 3)
- Semans, Mary, March 11, 1985; 13
  - Mary Semans Interview: Cassette 13, Side A, March 11, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Mary Semans Interview: cassette use copy, Side A, March 11, 1985, copied 11/03 (Box 2)
  - Mary Semans Interview: CD use copy, March 11, 1985 (Box 2)
- Turner, Bill, January 23, 1985; 14
  - Bill Turner Interview: Cassette 3, Side B, January 23, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Bill Turner Interview: cassette use copy, Side B, January 23, 1985, copied 11/03 (Box 2)
  - Bill Turner Interview: Transcript, January 23, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Bill Turner Interview: CD use copy, January 23, 1985 (Box 2)
- Watson, Richard, March 4, 1985; 15
  - Richard Watson Interview: Cassette 10, Side A, March 4, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Richard Watson Interview: cassette use copy, Side A, March 4, 1985, copied 11/03 (Box 2)
  - Richard Watson Interview: CD use copy, March 4, 1985 (Box 2)
- Williams, Fred, February 15, 1985; 16
  - Fred Williams Interview: Cassette 7, Side A, February 15, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Fred Williams Interview: Transcript, February 15, 1985 (Box 4)
- Williams, Janice, February 13, 1985; 17
  - Janice Williams Interview: Cassette 6, Side A, February 13, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Janice Williams Interview: Transcript, February 13, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Janice Williams Interview: CD use copy, February 13, 1985 (Box 2)
- Unidentified, undated; 18
  - Unidentified Interviewee: Cassette 1, Side A, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified Interviewee: Cassette 2, Side A, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified Interviewee: Cassette 11, Side B, undated (Box 1)